Jatin Sharma

Data Engineer

+91 8527785877 jatinsharma02100@gmail.com

Objective

Having experience as a Big Data Engineer, proficient at building analytical, data ingestion and data processing platforms using cloud services including Lambda, S3 and Kinesis. Also having experience in writing logical solutions using programming languages like Python, Java and CRUD operations using databases like MySQL, PostgreSQL and MongoDB.

Educational Qualification

Bachelor of Technology (Computer Science and Engineering), Lovely Professional University

Domain Knowledge and Technical Skills

Languages	Java, Python, C++, C, Shell-scripting
Database Management	MySQL, MongoDB, Trino, Delta Lake, PostgreSQL, Redis, Hive
Messaging System	Kafka, Kinesis
Big Data Frameworks	PySpark, Gobblin, Hadoop, AWS EMR
Application Tools	Databricks, Kubernetes, Docker, Airflow, Grafana, Prometheus
AWS Services	Lambda, EC2, S3, SNS, API Gateway, Aurora, DynamoDb, Redshift
Version Control	Git, Bitbucket
Operating System	Linux, Windows
Documentation	Github, Confluence

Experiences

Rakuten Symphony: March 2023 - Present

- Worked with Spark Jobs, Nifi flows to get a job running for scheduled or Trigger based methods.
- Experience in writing Scripts in python and Spark flow in Java.
- Generating Report from data using spark and Nifi flows.

XenonStack: June 2021 – Feb 2023

- Experience with Gobblin, Spark and integration of data from various sources.
- Worked on Building serverless and managed Lambda services for Data ingestion.
- Worked on developing Python and Java based projects.
- Experience with various messaging systems, such as Kafka and Kinesis
- Experience in Java as a backend with API support.
- Worked on different databases for data discovery and managing.
- Experience in developing pipelines using AWS and big data tools.
- Helped in designing architecture for a big data project.
- Experience in creating CI/CD pipelines in Jenkins with Bitbucket.

Capgemini India(January 2020- May 2020) Trainee

- Learned full stack technology, mainly focused on Spring-Boot, java, Mysql and Angular.
- Implemented real life Microservices Projects after learning these technologies.

Projects

BI Report Generation Tool

- BI reports created from telecom data using various customer's EMS.
- Used APIs for doing crud operation on data saved in Redis db.
- Generated reports to be saved in Minio and Email triggered to Customers for their reports.

EMS Integration

- A spark and Nifi collaborated flow which runs on kubernetes.
- Fetched data from Various customer's EMS and after refining data, reconcile operation performed on Graph db which contains telecom data.

Renewable Energy Data Management

- Data refinement and analysis for energy generation prediction.
- Pyspark Jobs written for data analysis and alerts to be generated in case of generators/turbine failure.
- Data to be stored in data-lake and after analysis generate graphs based on KPIs.
- Building serverless and managed Lambda services for Data ingestion.
- Databricks Jobs to calculate KPIs and aggregations.

Delivery Management

- Data management and migration on PostgreSQL, basically the data schema design.
- API Development in Python, APIs to be deployed on AWS lambda.
- Learned about vehicle Routing Problem and various APIs solution Providers for it.

Data Discovery and Catalogue Tool

- ETL of data from different sources to sinks.
- Learned and explored open-source tools that were used in Project Architecture.
- Research and build solution for tech stack used in project
- API Development in Springboot Java, as a wrapper for multiple tools used in this project.

Certification

- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner Certification.
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Fundamentals.

Personal Details

Permanent Address Saho, Chamba, Himachal Pradesh, India

Date of Birth 01 October 1998

Language proficiency English, Hindi, Punjabi

Hobbies/Interest Cricket, Playing Guitar, Writing